<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reuelation of the true Minerua The effect of this booke. Who on earth be gods: and by what meanes mortall men may bee made immortall.</title>
            <author>Blenerhasset, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840351</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 175:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reuelation of the true Minerua The effect of this booke. Who on earth be gods: and by what meanes mortall men may bee made immortall.</title>
                  <author>Blenerhasset, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the three Cranes in the Vintree by Thomas Dawson, for Thomas Woodcoke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Thomas Blener Hasset.</note>
                  <note>A verse eulogy of Queen Elizabeth.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *⁴ **²  A-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for a fleuron.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:1"/>
            <p>A Reuelation of the true <hi>Minerua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The effect of this booke.Who on earth be gods: and by what meanes mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men may bee made immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. Lxxxii.</bibl>
               <p>God ſtandeth in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the gods: hee is Iudge amongſt the gods.</p>
            </q>
            <p>1582.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>engraved decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:2"/>
            <head>To the very vertuous and my <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Lady, the Lady</hi> Leighton, one of the Ladies of the Queenes Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Chamber: the Pilgrime <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth a long and happie life, with ſuch increaſe</hi> of honour, as her Ladiſhips godly indeuours doe deſerue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow farre little Englande (my verie good Ladie) doeth in perfecte felicitie ſurpaſſe all the large king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the worlde, that trauell and ſmall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience which I haue had, hath ſufficiently taught mee: and in truth (were it not that the generall plentie of paſſing much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth make a great multitude of people to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in many reſpectes their dueties,) I would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting ſtedfaſtly beleeue that the Sunne it ſelfe neither doth, nor euer hath ſhined vppon any place, whoſe proſperitie might compare with this Ilandes: brought in deede to that worthie paſſe by the great good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſinguler induſtry of the Queenes Maieſties moſt excellent wiſdome. The due conſideration wherof, did moue mee continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to force my ſelfe in the praiſe of ſo great a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, and finding my weakeneſſe equall with mine vnworthines, I was ſtill reſtrained from that atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, and had indeede neuer attempted but that neceſſitie
<pb facs="tcp:4849:3"/> conſtraineth the ignoraunt to ſpeake when the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned be ſilent, &amp; the truth may with great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation be vttered out of the mouth of a childe. At my laſt return out of the maine Ocean, being entred into that brod &amp; boyſtrous bay of Portingale, there (I may truely ſay) amongeſt the moſte mightie and greateſt ouergrowne Seas in the worlde, the ſtrength of my deſire ſo preuailed, as it forced me (euen there) ſolemnely to vow, preſently after mine arriuall I woulde indeuour to ſtraine my breath to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, ſo to ſounde foorth her excellent praiſe, who of a barbarous Ile hath made a moſt floriſhing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. And beeing arriued in that pleaſant <hi>Tempe,</hi> immediatly ſolitarie contemplation ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted mee with the heauenly diuine powers, that not by imagination, but with preſent familiare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, I was continually conuerſaunt with the <hi>Muſes,</hi> with all learnings Ladies, euen with the anſient Gods and Goddeſſes themſelues, who haue repaide my diligent ſeruice with a ſmall habilitie to vſe my penne as a proper inſtrumente againſt yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome idlenes, and a ſharpe ſwoorde to vanquiſhe her brutiſh daughter blinde ignorance mother to error, the dreadfull vndoer of mankinde. By this meanes I filled of late fiue queeres of paper with mine owne deuiſes, if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eſteeme that his which the great worldemaker, I knowe not by what ſecrete di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine infuſion conuaieth into him, which booke for that it is in deed but a brief repetitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Queenes maieſties due deſerued praiſes, therfore I did intitle it
<pb facs="tcp:4849:3"/> 
               <hi>A Reuelation of the true Minerua:</hi> in whithe diſcourſe for that it pleaſeth many of the worthieſt that euer liued to vtter ſome ſpeeches in the praiſe of her moſt excellent Maieſtie, and to ſurrender and reſigne ouer their titles, beeing as it woulde ſeemee, prouoked thereto by her maieſties due deſarts, I not able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale that part, haue abruptly rent it from the reſte which made it once more beautifull. And becauſe your Ladiſhips exceeding great wiſdom hath made you a very worthy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of her maieſties moſt roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Courte, and hath inriched you with ſuch credite as you may mightily defende all godly and good indeuours, hauing your place continually very neere vnto her maieſties elbow, therfore I haue ſet foorth this firſt part vnder your tuition, hoping that the matter therein contained ſhall pleaſe euen as many as ſhall reade it, and thus your Ladiſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant doth end, wiſhing vnto you in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect your heartes deſires.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:4"/>
            <head>The Printer to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader, the intricate ſence of ſome things contayned in this ſmal treatiſe, may induce thy doubtfull minde into diuers iudgementes: therefore by obſeruing the Alphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beticall order ſet down in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and ſo conferring the notes which I haue heare prefixed with the authours diſcourſe, thou ſhalt (I doubt not,) finde a light ſufficient to leade thee tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe that darkneſſe, and thou vnderſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his intent wilt (I hope) remaine ſufficiently ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, which thing I hartily wiſhe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEcauſe that diuers verie good Philoſophers haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prited <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> this worde * <hi>Saturne</hi> to ſignifie the plentifull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of a minde endued with true vnderſtanding, deriuing it from the greeke woorde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: becauſe alſo in his time the golden worlde was in the moſt flouriſhing eſtate: therefore hee is here brought in, as one indued with the true vnderſtanding how to gouerne and rule a common weale: and ſo generally throughout this treatiſe, when any one whom the heathen for his woorthineſſe woorſhipped as a god is rehearſed, not the man, but the vertue which made him of ſo great eſtimation is to be regarded, and in this place the author with great admiration, finding all vertue, goodnes and godlineſſe, to concurre in a woman, becauſe he thinketh it no heriſie to affirme that euery good man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the place of a Maieſtrate is a god: therefore his intent
<pb facs="tcp:4849:4"/> is, that they whom vertue made goddes, ſhoulde create this goddeſſe, the very beloued of God, on whom God hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly beſtowed his great and beſt bleſſinges without meaſure, and thus he taketh his exordium from the <hi>Pſal. 82</hi> God ſtandeth in the congregation of the gods, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallas</hi> and <hi>Minerua</hi> by the authoritie of many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> woulde ſeeme both to bee but one: becauſe <hi>Pallas</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iupiter</hi> is called by the name of <hi>Minerua:</hi> yet this is moſt certayn, we reade but of one <hi>Pallas</hi> whoſe name is deriued of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſhee is of ſome called <hi>Bellona</hi> the goddeſſe of warre, of other <hi>Tritonia,</hi> taking that name of the Fenne in which ſhe was firſt founde: ſhee was compted the goddeſſe of humaine knowledge, and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth her <hi>Scientiarum &amp; prudentiae dea:</hi> but we read of <hi>5. Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uae:</hi> all the Philoſophers, and eſpecially <hi>Tully</hi> (contrary to the opinion of manie Poets) do call one of them <hi>Diſciplina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; Sapientiae dea,</hi> the great and greateſt goddeſſe, euen ſhee who had the knowledge of heauenly wiſedome: but howe ſo euer it was his intent is to ſhowe that worldly wit is of none effect without heauenly wiſedome, and for that cauſe <hi>Pallas</hi> doth here lament the loſſe of <hi>Mineruae,</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it not poſſible that the pollitike lawes of any common weale can bee of ſufficient force to beate downe ſinne, and to bridle the ranging deſires of mans diſpoſition with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diuinitie, and that the bodie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be brought to obey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie lawe, except that the working of the conſcience bee the chiefe cauſe thereof: and ſo he proceedeth to his purpoſe, to prooue that heauenly wiſedome is the knowledge and feare of God, and ſhee which is indued therewith, doth well deſerue to be called <hi>Minerua,</hi> the very true goddeſſe of wiſedome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alecto</hi> that ſpitefull furieſſe of hell (for ſo haue the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> Auncients tearmed hatred and malice) doth vpon no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion deuiſe to hurt the happie, and ſuch as by vertue doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende vnto the toppe of fortunes wheele, &amp; to aduaunce the vnworthie: therfore here he bringeth in <hi>Galathea,</hi> a light &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4849:5"/> very wanton woman, and thereby may be ſeene howe blind ſpite and hatred are: whoſe deſire is alwayes to deſtroy the vertuous, and to aduaunce the wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> There is nothing elſe contayned in this verſe but a Poeticall deſcription of a deuiſe, ſuch as the Popes holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is full of, eſpecially when he woulde extinguiſhe the light of the Goſpel, and as this verſe ſeemeth to haue no ſence, ſo his deuiſes haue no force, therefore it obſerueth a certayne <hi>Decorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:5"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Poore Pilgrime who ſeekes the circle rounde</l>
               <l>Of all the worlde to finde his heartes deſire,</l>
               <l>On tope of hie <hi>Pernaſſas</hi> hill hee found</l>
               <l>This booke, which al the <hi>Muſes</hi> did admire,</l>
               <l>With golden chain on deske of Genepire</l>
               <l>Faſt lockt it lay vpon <hi>Apollos</hi> ſeate.</l>
               <l>This in his breſt did kindle firſt the fire,</l>
               <l>Both night and day he did the Gods intreate,</l>
               <l>Long time hee ſerude with trickling droppes of ſweate</l>
               <l>Like drudge to learnings Ladies ſmall and great:</l>
               <l>And in the ende they gaue him for his hyre</l>
               <l>Such knowledge as of them hee did require.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minerua</hi> nowe reuealed is renownde,</l>
               <l>For fame her name and due deſart doth ſounde:</l>
               <l>Her happie head with goodly crowne is crownde,</l>
               <l>Long may ſhee liue and clime in honour hier,</l>
               <l>All meanes remoude that may moue her to ire</l>
               <l>The Pilgrime praies, doubting his owne retyre.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Goe ſtreight and feare not.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:6"/>
            <head>A Reuelation of the true <hi>Minerua.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie <hi>Ioue,</hi> he <hi>Saturne</hi> ſage did ſende, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               </l>
               <l>Commanding <hi>Mars,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercury</hi> to meet,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> paſſing prudent did attend:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Neptune</hi> left the ſeas, and all his fleete,</l>
               <l>The God of gods, theſe Goodly Gods did greete:</l>
               <l>Then thus he ſaide, let it be knowen by you,</l>
               <l>Whom I on earth moſt worthie doe auowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foreſpent with ſpeede, conſumde well neere with haſte,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas,</hi> ſhee there did piteouſly complaine, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/>
               </l>
               <l>Both I, and all the worlde is quite digraſt,</l>
               <l>My deare ſiſter, <hi>Minerua</hi> mine, in vaine</l>
               <l>I liue alas, for now there doth remaine,</l>
               <l>No no, not one <hi>Minerua</hi> done away,</l>
               <l>Which in her place is meete to beare the ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> mourne, and mourne they may for mee</l>
               <l>Sith goddeſſe ſhee of greateſt grace is gone,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Pallas</hi> I perplext with miſerie,</l>
               <l>Am left alone, (alas) and all alone:</l>
               <l>To you, you gods my ſtate I doe bemone,</l>
               <l>And if you will haue <hi>Pallas</hi> ſtill remaine,</l>
               <l>Then you a newe <hi>Minerua</hi> muſt ordaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> ſate with <hi>Saturne</hi> by his ſide,</l>
               <l>Hence <hi>Mercury,</hi> goe get thee hence hee ſaide,</l>
               <l>Doe ſeeke and ſearche through all the worlde ſo wide</l>
               <l>For her, who may bee newe <hi>Minerua</hi> made,</l>
               <l>Whoſe due deſerued fame ſhall neuer fade.</l>
               <l>The winged God went thence as ſwift as winde:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Saturne</hi> ſage did thus declare his minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:7"/>
               <l>All ſauage then like tearing Tigers fell,</l>
               <l>more bruite then beaſtes, there luſt moſt lewd was law:</l>
               <l>Men liude when I a man with men did dwell,</l>
               <l>Then men by men were rent and eaten rawe:</l>
               <l>From wicked wilde euen I theſe men did drawe</l>
               <l>To ciuile life, by my good gouernment:</l>
               <l>They were inclinde to knowe what reaſon ment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then lawes I made, and right at laſt did raigne,</l>
               <l>All men with one conſent put to their hande:</l>
               <l>From hilles and woods in the moſt pleaſant plaine</l>
               <l>men met like friendes, and as they there did ſtand,</l>
               <l>Both how, and who, ſhould rule, and till the land</l>
               <l>I did ordaine, cities and townes they then</l>
               <l>did builde, of beaſtes, they were by mee made men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then none did eate the ſweete of others ſweat,</l>
               <l>For <hi>thine</hi> by right, and merie <hi>mine</hi> I made,</l>
               <l>Therefore a God of all the gods moſt great</l>
               <l>They me ordainde, my fame can neuer fade</l>
               <l>Till heauen and all the earth be quite decaide:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Saturne</hi> ſits aloft in ſeemely ſphere,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo doth <hi>Mars</hi> (ſaid <hi>Mars</hi>) as you ſhall heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy <hi>mine</hi> and <hi>thine</hi> did breede ſuch bitter ſtrife,</l>
               <l>From out the worlde when thou wert once away,</l>
               <l>As euerie man did ſeeke eche others life,</l>
               <l>That witleſſe will might haue the power of <hi>may</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To rule vnruld, to beare the chiefeſt ſway:</l>
               <l>Then king with king, the weakeſt went to wracke,</l>
               <l>And mightie <hi>mine</hi> made feeble <hi>thine</hi> his lacke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:7"/>
               <l>Then might was right, for all thy lawes were lame,</l>
               <l>The goodly ground with blood was then imbrude,</l>
               <l>Then warres and warlike weapons I did frame,</l>
               <l>And force perforce, I right againe renude,</l>
               <l>Moſt quiet peace my bloodie warres inſude:</l>
               <l>My trayned troupes of ſouldiers kept in awe,</l>
               <l>All ſuch whoſe lewdneſſe made their luſte a lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You greateſt gods doe graunt and giue me grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silenus</hi> ſage (all Satier like) did ſay:</l>
               <l>To tell a truth here in this preſſe and place:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> halfe amazde, his ſtory there did ſtay:</l>
               <l>They gaue him leaue, then he without delay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>men may bee gods, euen gods of great degree,</l>
               <l>Such gods muſt die like men, and ſo did wee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why, howe, and who, by God and men bee made,</l>
               <l>Of mortall men immortall gods giue eare,</l>
               <l>when due deſerued fame can neuer fade:</l>
               <l>Report by right aboue the earth ſhall reare</l>
               <l>All ſuch, and ſet their names in ſeemely ſphere,</l>
               <l>Such liue on earth more happie then the reſt:</l>
               <l>Such haue in heauen a bliſſe of al the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> did plant, and <hi>Ceres</hi> ſowde the grounde,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> deuiſde the ſwelling Seas to ſaile,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> for his learning was renownde:<note place="margin">Haec prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, illa ſapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae dea.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For worldly wit dame <hi>Pallas</hi> did preuaile,</l>
               <l>Euen ſhee who heere <hi>Mineruas</hi> want doth waile,</l>
               <l>Theſe all were gods by due deſart, and ſhee</l>
               <l>A goddeſſe, next <hi>Minerua</hi> by degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:8"/>
               <l>For heauenly wiſedome<note n="*" place="margin">Minerua</note> ſhee exceld eche one,</l>
               <l>Her knowledge was, the ſoule from ſinne to ſaue,</l>
               <l>Which knowledge nowe is knowne alas to none,</l>
               <l>For all the worlde it is ſo bounſing braue</l>
               <l>As none, no one doth thinke vpon his graue:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Sapiens</hi> diuine wiſdome bee dead,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Pallas</hi> may with teares conſume her bred.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diuinitie is made a masking coate,</l>
               <l>To compaſſe what the diueliſhe doe deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Deceite and craft hath ſet their force aflote,</l>
               <l>All men haue wit, and no man nowe is wiſe:</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Proteus</hi> proude they do themſelues diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>No Gods but Diuels, no men but beaſtes they bee:</l>
               <l>Practiſing craft and deepe hypocriſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As men before <hi>Saturnus</hi> time were rude,</l>
               <l>Nowe much more brute and ſauage they will bee,</l>
               <l>If care of conſcience doth not ſinne detrude:</l>
               <l>You muſt therefore erect diuinitie,</l>
               <l>And one ordaine of great and good degree,</l>
               <l>Who muſt poſſeſſe <hi>Mineruas</hi> former place,</l>
               <l>So all the worlde true knoweledge will imbrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then hee and they all ſilent ſodenlie,</l>
               <l>Their muſing mindes did mourne and maruaile much,</l>
               <l>That this the laſt and latter age ſhoulde bee</l>
               <l>Forlorne, the greeued Gods heere at did grutch.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Mercurie</hi> his quicke returne was ſuche,</l>
               <l>Like hagarde hauke from haughtie heauen hee ſell,</l>
               <l>And thus hee did to them his trauell tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:8"/>
               <l>Where <hi>Troy</hi> once ſtood no citie nowe doth ſtande,</l>
               <l>A rude vnlearned rowte in <hi>Thebs</hi> remayne,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Athens</hi> nowe there be a beaſtly bande,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rome</hi> is rude her vaunting is in vayne:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo is <hi>France,</hi> all <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spayn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Liuye</hi> liues, no <hi>Tully</hi> can bee found,</l>
               <l>There is not one good Poët on the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That haughtie hill <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> heauenly hie</l>
               <l>For learning where the louly Laurell grewe,</l>
               <l>The bramble brier hath got the victorie:</l>
               <l>The bankes once braue with flowres of goodly hewe,</l>
               <l>All <hi>Helecon</hi> is blacke with moulded blewe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Permeſſus</hi> ſpringes be drie, the <hi>Nymphes</hi> be dead,</l>
               <l>The gorgious garlands gone, the <hi>Muſes</hi> flead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The warres hath wipt what worthie was away,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Barbarye</hi> doth <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> deuoure,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turke,</hi> the <hi>Moore,</hi> the prince of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They dayly do increaſe in ſtrength and power,</l>
               <l>They learning lothe, they build like beaſtes their bower</l>
               <l>In igoraunce, they feare nor God nor diuell,</l>
               <l>They hate the good, they honour what is euill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet I am ſent that Phoenix rare to finde</l>
               <l>Whom all in vaine I ſeeke and can not ſee,</l>
               <l>And yet ſhee liues, and is of <hi>Saturns</hi> kinde,</l>
               <l>Begot by <hi>Mars,</hi> preſerud by <hi>Ioue,</hi> and ſhee</l>
               <l>Remaynes aliue, in place not knowne to mee,</l>
               <l>The firme of all the worlde my ſelfe haue ſought,</l>
               <l>Yet her to finde the Oracle hath taught.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:9"/>
               <l>Where <hi>Arctike poole</hi> with <hi>Guardes</hi> doth ſtand</l>
               <l>L. and two<note place="margin">Lacking a third part.</note> degrees from lande</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minerua</hi> doth remaine:</l>
               <l>Where want of warre and quiet peace</l>
               <l>Hath cloid the countrey with increaſe</l>
               <l>of gold and goodly graine,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Troynouant,</hi> where <hi>Athens</hi> newe,</l>
               <l>where noble <hi>Nymphes</hi> do dwell,</l>
               <l>Where manie modeſt <hi>Muſes</hi> be,</l>
               <l>euen ſuch as do excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This greateſt goddeſſe there in throne</l>
               <l>Of higheſt dignitie alone</l>
               <l>doth ſit, and beare the ſway:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Olympus</hi> there, <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> hie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Permeſſus</hi> ſpringes be neuer drie,</l>
               <l>the ground is greene and gay:</l>
               <l>The Palme and Laurell there doth growe,</l>
               <l>euen there her biding is,</l>
               <l>Out from the worlde, yet on the grounde,</l>
               <l>euen in a place of bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There comes quoth noble <hi>Neptune</hi> to my mind</l>
               <l>That ſame of yore which ſober <hi>Sybill</hi> ſaide,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Mercurie</hi> in vaine ſhall ſeeke to finde:</l>
               <l>When all the worlde with warres ſhall be diſmaide:</l>
               <l>When learninges light ſhall ſeeme to be decayde:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Neptune</hi> then reioyce with triple mace,</l>
               <l>Let all the gods depart and giue him place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where at the gods greatly greeued did frowne,</l>
               <l>And ſaide, the ſea could not the lande excead:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:9"/>
               <l>But ſuddainely there was a goodly crowne</l>
               <l>With garlandes gay on noble <hi>Neptunes</hi> head,</l>
               <l>Imbroderd braue in romane letters redde</l>
               <l>All percell gilt, and burniſhed with blewe,</l>
               <l>The truth was ſet, and thus it did inſewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The tearing tract of time hath waſted and worne out the worthie,</l>
               <l>The mightie maine now may mourne ſuch loſſe, ſith the ſea hath her glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The greeued gods did maruell all amazde,</l>
               <l>Such vnknowne ſightes vpon this crowne were ſeene,</l>
               <l>About the toppe a ſwelling ſea was rayſde:</l>
               <l>In which a chalkie cliffe with medowes greene,</l>
               <l>There in on ſtately throne a royall Queene,</l>
               <l>A pranſing <hi>Pegaſus</hi> ſtood by the dame,</l>
               <l>And on his backe ſat euerlaſting fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On hieſt toppe a heauenly angell ſtood,</l>
               <l>Harde by his ſide a Harraulde had his place,</l>
               <l>From raging ſeas, euen from the <hi>Ocean</hi> flood</l>
               <l>Appearde a prince, bolde <hi>Brutus</hi> by his grace,</l>
               <l>To Harraulde he declarde his royall race:</l>
               <l>The king at armes his petigree he pende,</l>
               <l>The Angel markte and did his miſſe amende,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Queene to noble <hi>Brutus</hi> blood was found</l>
               <l>By long deſent alied linially,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneas</hi> he who was ſo much renownde</l>
               <l>From him did <hi>Brute</hi> deſcende ſucceſſiuely:</l>
               <l>The wandering prince had his natiuitie</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>For him who was the eldeſt ſonne, in ſeat</l>
               <l>His grandſier ſat, of all the gods moſt great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſeat wherein this courtly Queene did ſit</l>
               <l>was Rubie rare, none ſeene forſice ſo great,</l>
               <l>a golden globe was vnder both her feete,</l>
               <l>a comely cloude did compaſſe all the ſeate,</l>
               <l>the ſea in vayne the cloude and globe did beate</l>
               <l>with foming froth, about her heauenly heade</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> perſaude a poſie, which ſhee reade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not ſuch a godeſſe againe in <hi>Aſia, Europ,</hi> or <hi>Affricke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>for vertue, great degree, for her magnanimitie,</l>
               <l>Nowe let <hi>Apollo</hi> giue place, let <hi>Neptune</hi> ſit in the chiefe ſeat,</l>
               <l>ſith in his ſea ſhe doth dwel, ruling a world at her wil,</l>
               <l>Bliſſed &amp; bliſſed againe, three times thriſe happie <hi>minerua,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with thee and thine eſtate no mortal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Pan</hi> (when <hi>Neptune</hi> had <hi>Apollos</hi> place)</l>
               <l>that rurall god and clowniſhe ruſtikes king,</l>
               <l>with ſhepheardes three attending on his grace,</l>
               <l>he plide his pipe, the one of them did ſing,</l>
               <l>the ſecond ſighth, the third his handes did wring,</l>
               <l>when paſtor <hi>Pan</hi> perſaude their pitious plight,</l>
               <l>his pipe laide down he made his men reſight</l>
               <l>their cauſe of care.</l>
               <l>From walled towne I <hi>Bembus</hi> wonted was</l>
               <l>a mightie maſſe of money once a yeere</l>
               <l>full xl. crownes I did returne, alas</l>
               <l>nowe xx. grootes I can not compaſſe cleere,</l>
               <l>my ſtocke, my ſtore, my houſhold ſtuffe moſt deere,</l>
               <l>I ſpend, and ſpoyle, and all to none auayle,</l>
               <l>lawgh he that liſt, <hi>Bembus</hi> ſhall weepe and wayle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:10"/>
               <l>On pleaſant pipe to play did pleaſe me much,</l>
               <l>I did delight ſweete ditties to indight:</l>
               <l>But nowe the woes of wretched warres be ſuch</l>
               <l>As nothing els but howe in fielde to fight,</l>
               <l>And howe to keepe the flocke from ſouldiers ſight:</l>
               <l>That rauening woolfe, whoſe neuer filled mawe</l>
               <l>With rage doth make his wicked will a lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poore <hi>Colon</hi> I, and careful <hi>Comma</hi> ſhee</l>
               <l>My weded wife, once happie, nowe forlorne,</l>
               <l>Let vs complayne of fortunes crueltie,</l>
               <l>The countries grace, and nowe the countries ſcorne,</l>
               <l>X. men, v. flockes, v. plowes, to ſowe my corne</l>
               <l>I keept, but nowe the greater is my care</l>
               <l>My flockes be ſtolne, my fruitfull fieldes be bare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The people for the princes pride are plagde,</l>
               <l>It falleth to the faultleſſe ſubiectes lot,</l>
               <l>To double drinke in cruel cuppe of care,</l>
               <l>When peruerſe princes madding minde doth dote:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellona</hi> then doth ſounde a dolefull note,</l>
               <l>Then blooddie men of warre the ſweete doth eate</l>
               <l>Without regard of vs the ſhepheardes ſweate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My <hi>Bembus</hi> deare thou knoweſt this Sommer laſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe armie laide all leuell with the grounde</l>
               <l>Our corne halfe ripe, our vines were ſpoild as faſt,</l>
               <l>Our townes be burnt, our woods worth many a pound</l>
               <l>Be quite deſtroyde, and where may nowe be founde</l>
               <l>One hedge, or ditch, not torne nor troden downe,</l>
               <l>This curſed crop we reape from hie renowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:11"/>
               <l>In winter nowe when <hi>Boreas</hi> bitter blaſt</l>
               <l>Forbiddes in field that armed men ſhoulde meete,</l>
               <l>A greater griefe we countrey men do taſt,</l>
               <l>Wee ceſſed are, the ſouldier eates the ſweete</l>
               <l>Of all our toile, a thing nor iuſt nor meete,</l>
               <l>Such is my ſtate: yet this my hireling</l>
               <l>when <hi>Pan</hi> doth pipe what doth he then but ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſing thy ſeruaunt muſt good <hi>Colon,</hi> he</l>
               <l>Doth hope to haue (as he before hath had)</l>
               <l>A place of reſt exempt from miſerie,</l>
               <l>You both (I thinke) do ſinne to be ſo ſadde,</l>
               <l>Take mine aduiſe and be you euer glad,</l>
               <l>Do followe mee, forſake theſe fieldes though knowne,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe can giue the like they be mine owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For I <hi>Epizenes</hi> a paſtor am,</l>
               <l>Though nowe thy man yet I my ſelfe keepe men,</l>
               <l>With in my fieldes ſkipes many a luſtie lambe,</l>
               <l>I dwell where beefe and bacon meate for men,</l>
               <l>where milke and honie floweth like the fenne:</l>
               <l>I dwell where want of warre and quiet reſt</l>
               <l>Doth plainely proue <hi>Brittaine</hi> to be the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Epizenes</hi> thou ſeemſt to haue no ſence,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bembus</hi> ſhall proue thee mad or ignorant,</l>
               <l>If ſo it be, why didſt thou runne from thence?</l>
               <l>wherefore? becauſe all thinges they be ſo ſcant</l>
               <l>where thou doeſt dwell, that naked neede and want</l>
               <l>Did driue thee thence, my neighbour <hi>Colon</hi> can</l>
               <l>Report thy ſtate, when firſt thou wert his man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:11"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bembus,</hi> do heare the ſtorie of my ſtate,</l>
               <l>Cloyd with the bliſſe which nowe I doe deſire,</l>
               <l>I knowe not what the frowarde force of fate</l>
               <l>I being well, did make mee to aſpire,</l>
               <l>By trauell I did thinke to clime vp hier,</l>
               <l>Thus not content in paradize to dwell,</l>
               <l>ſeeking for heauen, I founde out hatefull hell,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By ſea and lande my ſelfe with reſtleſſe toyle</l>
               <l>The circle rounde of all the worlde haue ſought,</l>
               <l>Since firſt I left my louely natiue ſoyle</l>
               <l>with deere expenſe my knoweledge I haue brought,</l>
               <l>The ſpice of <hi>Spayne, Canary</hi> wine is nought,</l>
               <l>The grapes of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> the fruite of <hi>Italye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor pleaſant fieldes in <hi>Flanders</hi> pleaſeth mee,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What taxe, what tolle, what tribute do they pay?</l>
               <l>with dayly warres, what wretched liues they leade?</l>
               <l>Kinges they do cauſe continuall decay,</l>
               <l>Their ſubiectes liue in daily doubt and dread.</l>
               <l>They wofull wightes, do hate their hurtfull head,</l>
               <l>They curſe their kings, like ſlaues which make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerue,</l>
               <l>They till and toile, and yet for food they ſtarue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oppreſſion rules with cruell tyrannie,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Spayne</hi> is ſpitefull ſuperſtition ſpread:</l>
               <l>Harde roughnes doth remaine in <hi>Germany,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fidelitie from faithleſſe <hi>Fraunce</hi> was flead:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Italie</hi> fancie is ſuprime head:</l>
               <l>Blinde ignoraunce in <hi>Barbary</hi> remaine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Turke</hi> doth loue the diuell, and God diſdaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:12"/>
               <l>But none of theſe in Britayne braue abide,</l>
               <l>Where godeſſe great <hi>Elizabeth</hi> doth raine.</l>
               <l>For God almightie with his grace doth gyde</l>
               <l>Her highneſſe heart, and all her courtly trayne,</l>
               <l>That happie he who may with her remaine:</l>
               <l>Both poore and rich doth quietly poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>Their owne, the hauen of heauenly happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When luſt moſt leude made iuſtice leaue the lawe:</l>
               <l>And vice deſtroyd dame vertues ſtately ſtile:</l>
               <l>Diuinitie eſteemde not worth a ſtrawe:</l>
               <l>Theſe three diſdaind were baniſht to exile,</l>
               <l>They left the lande, on ſeas they ſaild a while,</l>
               <l>And at the laſt on <hi>Brittayne</hi> braue they fell,</l>
               <l>Where queene <hi>Eliza</hi> made theſe Ladies dwel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Religion firſt a certaine ſigne of grace,</l>
               <l>Not next, but in her high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s heauenly heart,</l>
               <l>Amidſt her minde vertue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take her place:</l>
               <l>Shee did commaund Iuſtice not to depart</l>
               <l>From her right hande, nor from her ſide to ſtart:</l>
               <l>Then thus ſhee ſpake, during my doubtfull date</l>
               <l>I will bee Queene, you three ſhall rule my ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Epizenes</hi> (quoth) <hi>Pan</hi> if <hi>Bembus</hi> bee,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Colon</hi> with his <hi>Comma</hi> be content,</l>
               <l>Wee will depart to place vnknowen with thee,</l>
               <l>And ſell or let the ſheep courſes for rent:</l>
               <l>Some god perhappes thy ſelfe hath hither ſent,</l>
               <l>Vs to conduct to place where as wee may</l>
               <l>Liue like the men in rich <hi>Europia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:12"/>
               <l>And better much for libertie and gaine,</l>
               <l>if ſo you will, then let vs hence away.</l>
               <l>The windes bee good, doe neuer thinke it payne</l>
               <l>to ſayle the Seas, within a month wee may</l>
               <l>haue happie hauen, and bee in bleſſed bay:</l>
               <l>my ſelfe will take that ſtately charge in hande,</l>
               <l>to guide your courſe, and winne the wiſhed land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With this croſſe ſtaffe, wherewith I wonted was,</l>
               <l>height, length, and breadth of euery thing to tell,</l>
               <l>with that, and with an Aſtrolob of braſſe,</l>
               <l>Globe, Compaſſe, a Nocturnall will doe well,</l>
               <l>with theſe, and with my Carde which doth excell,</l>
               <l>I ſo will ſaile, as you ſhall vnderſtande:</l>
               <l>that <hi>Palinurus</hi> hate the Helme in hande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Titan</hi> ſittes in middayes circle ſeate,</l>
               <l>when goodly Guardes doth Artike Pole diſplaie,</l>
               <l>then ſhall you ſee a ſhephearde doe the feate,</l>
               <l>and perfectly direct you on your way:</l>
               <l>ouer the place where as I meane to ſtay,</l>
               <l>The North ſtarre ſtands at fiftie two degree,</l>
               <l>That height founde out, wee finde felicitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They were content, and as they did depart,</l>
               <l>The greateſt god of all this goodly traine,</l>
               <l>I ſee (hee ſaide) thou haſt the Sea mans Art:</l>
               <l>My <hi>Mercurie</hi> hath ceaſeleſſe ſought in vaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minerua</hi> there, <hi>Minerua</hi> doth remaine:</l>
               <l>Goe foorth my ſonne and trauaile to newe <hi>Troy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee went, and came, and brought encreaſe of ioy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:13"/>
               <l>For as you ſee the ſwifteſt Swallowes wing,</l>
               <l>Doth cut the ſkie, and leaues her haunt behind:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Mercurie</hi> the poſt of Gods did bring</l>
               <l>His meſſage backe, whome <hi>Homer</hi> hath aſſignde:</l>
               <l>A meſſenger to them of heauenly kinde:</l>
               <l>To whome he did with ſpeede his ſpeeche adreſſe,</l>
               <l>And thus what hee had ſeene he did expreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My trauaile proues the <hi>Oracle</hi> moſt true,</l>
               <l>The workmahſhip on <hi>Neptunes</hi> noble crowne,</l>
               <l>Doth repreſent halfe the deſerued due,</l>
               <l>Of her the greateſt goddeſſe of renowne:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minerua</hi> liues, let <hi>Pallas</hi> ceaſe to frowne,</l>
               <l>She is aliue, my ſelfe her grace haue ſeene,</l>
               <l>In maieſtie, of <hi>Britayne</hi> braue the Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To wh m when firſt I made my meſſage knowne,</l>
               <l>And ſaide, O Queene the gods doe thee ſalute,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> himſelfe whoſe fame about is blowne:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars Neptune,</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> great by brute,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> thy younger ſiſter hath a ſute</l>
               <l>vnto thy grace, they all, but chiefly ſhe,</l>
               <l>Sent mee to know thy ſtate and great degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Queene replide, I knowe no God but one</l>
               <l>And hee of heauen, who guides mee by his grace:</l>
               <l>The Heathen had their Gods which nowe bee gone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Idols I by Gods ſpell did deface:</l>
               <l>There is one God and him I doe imbrace,</l>
               <l>No ſiſter I, yet what they doe intende</l>
               <l>declare, for I all goodnes will defend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:13"/>
               <l>Moſt mightie prince <hi>Saturne</hi> doth ſignifie</l>
               <l>good gouernment: <hi>Neptune</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> of might</l>
               <l>By Sea and land in warre haught valiancie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> how diuinely to indight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> wiſdome to rule and raigne aright:</l>
               <l>Such vertues great from theſe men did deſcende,</l>
               <l>They are and ſhal be gods vnto the end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet baniſht nowe they liue in darke exile,</l>
               <l>For where is valure or good gouernemente?</l>
               <l>Learning hath left her former ſtately ſtile,</l>
               <l>From prudence craft her right with rage hath rent:</l>
               <l>The cauſe why theſe deſtreſſed Gods haue ſent</l>
               <l>me to this Ile, from that moſt mightie maine</l>
               <l>is this, they heare thy highneſſe here doth raigne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By right, ruling thie Realme with equitie,</l>
               <l>Heauenlie wiſdome and godly zeale doth reſt</l>
               <l>with thee, pitie and perfect pietie:</l>
               <l>God with his grace aboundantly hath bleſt</l>
               <l>thy grace, and thee inritcht aboue the reſt,</l>
               <l>They, (other) Princes of another kinde</l>
               <l>Doe baniſhe ſuch as thou doeſt ſeeke to finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hopeleſſe of helpe which when theſe gods did heare,</l>
               <l>They ſent in poſt on meſſage <hi>Mercury:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I am not fame which flyeth here and there</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mercurie</hi> deare dame, doeh ſignifie</l>
               <l>A meſſenger, and for the gods am I</l>
               <l>Sent with this ſute, if it may pleaſe thy grace,</l>
               <l>Both they and I will ſerue thee in this place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:14"/>
               <l>And then the Queene, my ſeruants? no, my ſaints,</l>
               <l>Copertiners of my crowne and dignitie:</l>
               <l>Let them leaue off their heeretofore complaints:</l>
               <l>Bid them come rule this mightie Realme with mee,</l>
               <l>And let them knowe my ſtate and great degree:</l>
               <l>Tell them that nothing can delight mee more,</l>
               <l>Then they whoſe names I chiefly doe adore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then might you ſee the prudent <hi>Pallas</hi> glade,</l>
               <l>And all her mourning garments done away,</l>
               <l>All her aſſiſtants ſighde and ſobd ful ſad:</l>
               <l>Reioyced nowe, and Solemnizde that day</l>
               <l>With ſonges, and making garlandes gorgeous gay:</l>
               <l>Then thus ſhee ſpake, good <hi>Mercury</hi> at large,</l>
               <l>Report the thinges committed to thy charge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">His replie.</note> Her heauenly hewe, her more then mortall grace,</l>
               <l>(For vertue may mortall immortall make,)</l>
               <l>Her ſtately ſteppes, her princelie royall race,</l>
               <l>Her Maieſtie makes mortall men to quake,</l>
               <l>Her dignitie doth make the gods to ſhake:</l>
               <l>When earthly eyes her highneſſe doe behold,</l>
               <l>They doe affirme her forme not from the moulde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ouer her head, angels with ſwordes in hande,</l>
               <l>Betwixt her eyes doth right remorſe remaine,</l>
               <l>Before her face the feare of God doth ſtande,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salomons</hi> bliſſe abideth in her braine,</l>
               <l>Her eares bee ſtopt to matters vilde and vaine:</l>
               <l>From goodlie lips her learned tongue doth tell</l>
               <l>The way to heauen, where ſhee no doubt doth dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:14"/>
               <l>Contented life within her minde doth reſt,</l>
               <l>Vpon her breaſt doth perfect bliſſe abide,</l>
               <l>And charitie doth ſit vpon her cheſt:</l>
               <l>A certaine ſure ſtate that cannot ſlide</l>
               <l>Is fixt as beſt beſeemes faſt to her ſide,</l>
               <l>Moſt worthie prayſe for her virginitie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi> neuer halfe ſo chaſte as ſhe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her arme doth rule a mightie Realme by right,</l>
               <l>Her hande doth giue eche one his due deſart,</l>
               <l>To walke in righteous wayes is her delight,</l>
               <l>From perfect path her feete doe not depart,</l>
               <l>Her ſteppes moſt ſtraight doe ſhew her heauenly heart,</l>
               <l>Vnder her feete raging reuenge doth couch,</l>
               <l>At her commaunde her valure to auouche.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When treaſons ſpightful, hid conſpiracies,</l>
               <l>They woulde vntwine her worthie warped twiſt:</l>
               <l>Theſe heauenly Angels then with <hi>Argus</hi> eies,</l>
               <l>Doe force the blooddie blade from traytours fiſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gotten gaine is heauie had I wiſt:</l>
               <l>When forraigne foes would reaue her princely crown,</l>
               <l>Then blacke reuenge doth beate their boaſtings down.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This true report whilſt <hi>Maias</hi> ſonne hath made,</l>
               <l>And brought the gods from maruaile to a maze,</l>
               <l>Withouten ſhape all ſubſtantleſſe a ſhade</l>
               <l>Appearde in ſight, on which they all did gaze,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bended browes an inwarde griefe did blaze:</l>
               <l>This ſhadowe ſeemde with all her might in vaine,</l>
               <l>To turne the wheele where mankinde doth remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:15"/>
               <l>On toppe whereof <hi>Minerua</hi> hath her place,</l>
               <l>A glorious ſeat by which but one did ſit,</l>
               <l>and hee not knowne, princes of royal race</l>
               <l>about the ſides in place for them moſt fit,</l>
               <l>A godly youth and of a worthie wit</l>
               <l>Was plaſt with them, whoſe mothers due deſart</l>
               <l>Quite from the wheele had laid her downe apart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alecto</hi> then, the breader of debate</l>
               <l>Though pale, and wane yet blewe with ruthfull rage,</l>
               <l>Fie fortune fie (quoth ſhe) fie on thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>A goddeſſe? no, thou wart in elder age,</l>
               <l>Contemned nowe of plowman, prince and page,</l>
               <l>No homage done, honour, nor ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>Come take reuenge of this contempt, ariſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By nature I all happineſſe doe hate,</l>
               <l>The giftes I giue are bitter griefes like gall,</l>
               <l>Hate, ſpight, malice, and madneſſe, ſtaie my ſtate,</l>
               <l>With theſe I dayly doe deuiſe to thrall</l>
               <l>All ſuch as ſit aloft in ſtately ſtal:</l>
               <l>My pleaſure is the fortunate to foyle,</l>
               <l>All my delight is in their ſpeedie ſpoyle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With mightie arme to turne this wheele make haſt:</l>
               <l>Let them belowe aboue in bliſſe remaine,</l>
               <l>My gorgeous <hi>Galathea</hi> is diſgraſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> Whom to aduance I toyle as yet in vaine,</l>
               <l>Of thee, and to thy grace ſhee doth complaine:</l>
               <l>Heare her at laſt, and let her not for aye</l>
               <l>By due deſart be drowned in decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:15"/>
               <l>But fortunes force was now of none auaile,</l>
               <l>When vices vilde to caue of cruell care</l>
               <l>Doe caſt, her power then can not preuaile:</l>
               <l>When godly life, and vertues very rare,</l>
               <l>When they aduaunce, what fickle fortune dare</l>
               <l>moleſt ſuch one, whom God in higheſt place</l>
               <l>hath ſet, whoſe ſteps be guided by his grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alecto</hi> lewd the hater of good hap</l>
               <l>when ſhe perceiude dame fortunes feeble force,</l>
               <l>Shee made about and ſpide a ſecond gap</l>
               <l>wherein ſhee leapt, O <hi>Pluto</hi> take remorſe</l>
               <l>on vs ſhe ſaid, with voice hollow and hoarce:</l>
               <l>Shee ſits thou ſeſt in higheſt dignitie,</l>
               <l>which doth deſtroy thy mightie monarchie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The worlde thou knoweſt, I all the worlde was thine,</l>
               <l>Thy caues were cramd, when heauen all emptie was,</l>
               <l>Blinde ignorance that mighty mother mine</l>
               <l>ſhee ruld, ſhee rainde, ſhe brought it ſo to paſſe</l>
               <l>That all was thine, euen ſhee maintaind the maſſe,</l>
               <l>And ſhee it was which gaue the triple crowne</l>
               <l>To him of <hi>Rome,</hi> of more then<note n="*" place="margin">Ironi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> muche renowme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now, (not from <hi>Apollos</hi> learned braine)</l>
               <l>Out from the ſtocke of <hi>Mars</hi> is ſprong a maide,</l>
               <l>Who doth both him, and thee, and mee diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeſt by her thy kingdome is decayd,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeſt her force, her fame can neuer fade,</l>
               <l>True knowledge ſhortly ſo ſhall ſtuffe the heauen,</l>
               <l>That all thy ſtate ſhal ſtand at ſixe and ſeuen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:16"/>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Pluto</hi> tell my <hi>Metropolitan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To no ſuch end he hath his princely place,</l>
               <l>Hee keepes the keyes, his might may bliſſe or ban,</l>
               <l>Yet dothe hee ſee and ſuffer this diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Tell him from mee I him and all his race</l>
               <l>will quite deſtroy except he doth pluck down,</l>
               <l>All ſuche as bee rebellers to my crowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did the Diuell with patience replie,</l>
               <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope had heard his princes minde,</l>
               <l>His heauie hearte in raging wrath did frie,</l>
               <l>In haſt, poſt haſt a counſaile hee aſſignde:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bals</hi> balling Prieſtes (not only bald but blinde,)</l>
               <l>From euery coaſt in flockes like Coutes they came,</l>
               <l>Thus ſpake the woolfe clad like a ſimple lambe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ghoſtly care with mercie mixt too muche,</l>
               <l>Hath brought contempt, curſing ſhall nowe preuaile:</l>
               <l>This ſtubborne wretched wicked worlde is ſuch.</l>
               <l>Nowe puniſhment and whippes of bitter bayle:</l>
               <l>They muſt and ſhall refourme, I will not faile,</l>
               <l>To plucke them downe with vengeance ruthfull reed:</l>
               <l>Which doe denie mee to bee ſupreme head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haue I the power to curſe, to bliſſe, to binde,</l>
               <l>To loſe, to ſend to heauen or els to hel?</l>
               <l>Or is this key and triple crowne aſſignde</l>
               <l>To me, to ſuffer them thus to rebell?</l>
               <l>No no, I will ſubdue them very well:</l>
               <l>To <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to mightie <hi>Spaine,</hi> to <hi>Italie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I <hi>Britane</hi> giue, <hi>Scotlande,</hi> and <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:16"/>
               <l>Whoſe princes proud are fled from former faith,</l>
               <l>And doe deuiſe to rob mee of the reſt,</l>
               <l>When as my ſtate was at the hieſt haigth</l>
               <l>Then happie he who with my toe was bleſt,</l>
               <l>Then all was mine from the'ſt vnto the weſt,</l>
               <l>Then on the backes of Emperours I trode<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Then who but I, there was none other God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But nowe alas I liue in lowe degree,</l>
               <l>A woman doth mee and my might defie,</l>
               <l>The Goſpel nowe my mortall enemie</l>
               <l>By meanes of her is preacht both farre and nie:</l>
               <l>As it reuiues, ſo I your pope doe die:</l>
               <l>As I do droupe, ſo you your ſelues muſt mourne,</l>
               <l>Looke well heereto before you be forlorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This carefull court in haſte it did deuiſe,</l>
               <l>It ſent forth ſectes, it traytors did retaine,</l>
               <l>Thoſe rebels fled for feare which faine woulde riſe,</l>
               <l>It made them practiſe matters vilde and vaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alectos Galathia</hi> did complayne</l>
               <l>Whome to aduaunce they haue, they do, and will,</l>
               <l>On feeble fort ſuch ſhow their ſlender skill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For as the ſeas do roare againſt the rocke</l>
               <l>In vaine, and windes no mountaines maie remooue,</l>
               <l>So there at <hi>Rome</hi> theſe forceleſſe prieſtes did flock</l>
               <l>None of their popiſh practizes would proue,</l>
               <l>Which did ſo much that mightie monſter moue,</l>
               <l>As ſtraight he did a holie league conclude,</l>
               <l>Meaning by might the Goſpel to detrude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:17"/>
               <l>Then <hi>Galathia</hi> preſently was bleſt,</l>
               <l>If he may bleſſe who coulde nor can not curſe,</l>
               <l>Hee made a ſhotte and yet the marke he miſt,</l>
               <l>Hee ſtretcht the ſtringes of his plentifull purſe</l>
               <l>In vaine, and all in vaine hee did disburſe</l>
               <l>His <hi>Peterpence,</hi> all thinges had ſuch ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>As well deſcrude his worſhips worthineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Which made him clap a loofe hooke to his ſaile,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> put on his conſidering cappe,</l>
               <l>A fruiteleſſe flower paſſing poore &amp; pale:</l>
               <l>Without or ſmell, or taſt, or ſence, or ſappe,</l>
               <l>A hidden hooke, a traine, a ſecrete trappe,</l>
               <l>Away the witch, the windes were not to ſcant,</l>
               <l>The fleete was rigde, and yet there was a want.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then from that borde he caſt his ſayles about,</l>
               <l>He did and doth an other drift deuiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alecto</hi> with her ſtobourne ſeruauntes ſtoute</l>
               <l>Doth further forth his diueliſhe enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>With falſe report to euery coaſte ſhe flies</l>
               <l>And filles the eares of euerie king with ire</l>
               <l>Againſt her grace to make them all conſpire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The preſent gods ſeeing this great turmoile,</l>
               <l>Made haſte with ſpeede her perſon to defende,</l>
               <l>Saide <hi>Saturne</hi> let vs keepe her from the foile,</l>
               <l>This wicked world ſhee all her force doth bend</l>
               <l>To ſinke ſuch as by vertue woulde aſcend.</l>
               <l>This is (ſaid <hi>Mars</hi>) a valiant troupe I trowe:</l>
               <l>which dare attempt one womans ouerthrowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And doth the diuell and he his depute there?</l>
               <l>Doe kinges conſult, and furies fierce of hell,</l>
               <l>My daughter from her hie eſtate to teare?</l>
               <l>Dare they againſt both <hi>Ioue</hi> and vs rebell?</l>
               <l>O hie deuiſe, their courage doth excell:</l>
               <l>They faine woulde frame the ouerthrowe of one</l>
               <l>which muſt and ſhall remaine when they are gone,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe pride, but firſt their rage we will reſiſt,</l>
               <l>Menacing <hi>Mars</hi> with eyes like flaming fire,</l>
               <l>His face ſhowde what was ſhrowded in his breſt:</l>
               <l>He made all that were preſent to admire</l>
               <l>At his reuenge, and dare they thus conſpire?</l>
               <l>They will (quoth hee) and I will doe the deede</l>
               <l>which ſhall preuaile, when ſhee ſhall ſtande in neede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> with ſecrete ſuddaine ioy reuiude,</l>
               <l>Forgetting quite her griefes forerunne ſhee ſaide,</l>
               <l>Attende and heare the ſong I haue contriude,</l>
               <l>Giue eare you gods, lende me your louing ayd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> thou the beſt that euer plaide</l>
               <l>Take Lute in hand, tune to the waters fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minerua</hi> liues, whom <hi>Pallas</hi> honor ſhall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Farewell you kinges of all the continent</l>
               <l>both farre and neare,</l>
               <l>Againſt both gods, and goodnes you be bent</l>
               <l>with ſworde and ſpeare,</l>
               <l>Therefore with you the furies fierce of hell,</l>
               <l>We with the vertuous Engliſh Queene will dwell,</l>
               <l>ſhe can not ſlide</l>
               <l>for we will ſide</l>
               <l>Her ſteppes, and make her fame excel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:18"/>
               <l>For true report with golden trumpe doth ſounde</l>
               <l>her worthie prayſe:</l>
               <l>But your reproch by rumour doth rebounde</l>
               <l>in the hie wayes</l>
               <l>Of all the worlde, ſo you in infamie</l>
               <l>Muſt liue, and ſhee in royall dignitie:</l>
               <l>howe can ſhee fade</l>
               <l>whom vertue made</l>
               <l>The greateſt godeſſe by degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reioyce you gods to ſing we will not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>nowe we haue founde</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt place of reſt and quiet peace</l>
               <l>vpon the grounde.</l>
               <l>For we ſhall ſit euen by her ſeemely ſide,</l>
               <l>Whoſe mightie maſe the golden world doth gide:</l>
               <l>ſo worthie a Queene</l>
               <l>was neuer ſeene,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe heauenly ſtate ſhall neuer ſlide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From ſtriking of his ſtringes <hi>Apollo</hi> ſtayde,</l>
               <l>VVhich brought this ſuddaine ende to <hi>Pallas</hi> ſong,</l>
               <l>His Lute laide downe hee thus vnto them ſaide,</l>
               <l>As wee be godes, ſo let vs do no wrong,</l>
               <l>you knowe the charge which doth to vs belong,</l>
               <l>Howe mightie <hi>Ioue</hi> the onely god aboue</l>
               <l>VVould vs on earth ſhowe whom he beſt doth loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If <hi>Pallas</hi> and the tried trueth doth proue</l>
               <l>The Engliſh Queene of all moſt worthie prayſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:18"/>
               <l>Then may wee boldely boaſt that God doth loue</l>
               <l>Her beſt, if moſt ſhee walketh in his wayes,</l>
               <l>VVhich if to proue make we no more delayes</l>
               <l>But let vs hence, for we with her will dwell</l>
               <l>If ſuch ſhee be, if ſo ſhee doth excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then her we may and will immortall make,</l>
               <l>A goddeſſe great <hi>Minerua</hi> be her name,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Mercury</hi> hee ſhall him ſelfe betake</l>
               <l>To all the worlde, and there he ſhall proclame</l>
               <l>Both farre and neare her due deſerued fame:</l>
               <l>All men that liue her grace they ſhall adore</l>
               <l>Both at this preſent time, and euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Pallas</hi> let it be as you haue ſaide,</l>
               <l>wee will depart, yet doubt not of the dame,</l>
               <l>Shee is by proofe and oracle diſplayde,</l>
               <l>Moſt certainelie I knowe ſhee is the ſame:</l>
               <l>And I before I hence depart, will frame</l>
               <l>A comely Coronet of goodly greene,</l>
               <l>which ſhall right well become a maiden Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And wee ſaide they will breake downe <hi>Floras</hi> bower</l>
               <l>Yeelding thereto the floweres of the fielde:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Syluanus</hi> then ſtept from his ſtately towre,</l>
               <l>And I thereto ſuch branches braue will yeelde</l>
               <l>(Saide hee,) as hath been ſeene but verie fielde,</l>
               <l>Of woodes, of groues, of goodly greene the god</l>
               <l>I am, you knowe they bowe if I but nod.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:19"/>
               <l>Though hatefull <hi>Hyems</hi> waſting winters rage,</l>
               <l>With bitter blaſtes my tender bowes doth bite:</l>
               <l>Yet friendly <hi>Ver</hi> her rigor doth aſwage,</l>
               <l>And all my groues with goodly greene doth dight:</l>
               <l>The modeſt <hi>Muſes</hi> flocke for their delight</l>
               <l>Amidſt my greene, they daily march for meede,</l>
               <l>They ſing, they daunce, they there, their fancies feede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVithin my groues ſuch ſacred trees doe growe</l>
               <l>As neuer will their louely greene forgoe,</l>
               <l>Them on your goddeſſe garlande I'le beſtowe,</l>
               <l>Not onely them, but many flowres moe,</l>
               <l>Hearbes of all ſortes if you will haue it ſo.</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Neptune,</hi> pearles and precious ſtones great ſtore</l>
               <l>I will ſupplie, what woulde <hi>Pallas</hi> haue more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then forth they went and gathered all was good,</l>
               <l>Great mightie bowes and branches home they brought,</l>
               <l>they did diſgrace eche forreſt, fielde, and wood.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> returnd who had his <hi>Indies</hi> ſought,</l>
               <l>From thence he Iewels which were neuer bought</l>
               <l>For price, nor pay, they were ſo paſſing rare:</l>
               <l>To order all <hi>Pallas</hi> had all the care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dame <hi>Flora</hi> with her nimble <hi>Nymphes</hi> came in,</l>
               <l>Euen there they did their louely lappes vnlade,</l>
               <l>And in her hande the prettie fairie Queene</l>
               <l>Shee helde a glaſſe, theſe flowres ſhall not fade,</l>
               <l>Them to preſerue this water I haue made:</l>
               <l>They ſhall not die, nor droup, but floriſh faire,</l>
               <l>Nor feele the force of Sommers ſwelting aire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:19"/>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> ix. ix. colours did preſent</l>
               <l>Of ſowing ſilke vntwined yet in twiſt,</l>
               <l>To ſowe, to weaue, to binde was their intent</l>
               <l>where need requirde, then with her faire fiſt</l>
               <l>A <hi>Morian</hi> maide when ſhee the place had bliſt,</l>
               <l>Chryſtall, Currall, Amber, Bugle ſhee</l>
               <l>Laide downe, and ſaide theſe for your gerland be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Graces</hi> called <hi>Charites</hi> came in,</l>
               <l>Two bagges, the third ſhee did a bottel beare,</l>
               <l>In which full twentie ſeueral roomes there bin</l>
               <l>All filde with water delicate and deare,</l>
               <l>Diſtilled all: and in the bagges there were</l>
               <l>Muske, Mirre, Siuit, and Ambergreece the beſt</l>
               <l>That hath bin ſeene, from th, eſt vnto the weſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They all as one imploide their ſecond care</l>
               <l>More buſie then the birde which buildes her neſt,</l>
               <l>To take the choice whoſe vertues were moſt rare,</l>
               <l>They litle ſlippes and branches of the beſt</l>
               <l>Did bring, they left and laide away the reſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> her ſelfe did worke this worthie wreath</l>
               <l>moſt paſſing braue aboue, and braue beneath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ix. noble worthies mightie <hi>Mars</hi> they prayde</l>
               <l>To paſſe with him to pleaſe their chiefe delight:</l>
               <l>Vij. ſages then they thus to <hi>Saturne</hi> ſaide</l>
               <l>wee will with thee to ſee this worthie wight:</l>
               <l>Three Marriners indude with deepe inſight</l>
               <l>Of ſeamans skill, worthie to frame a courſe</l>
               <l>where <hi>Neptune</hi> was in ſpight of <hi>Eols</hi> force:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:20"/>
               <l>A learned troupe vnto <hi>Apollo</hi> preſt,</l>
               <l>Of which were two inſeparable ſeemde,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silenus,</hi> tho like mouners, yet the beſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by deedes and doctrine deemd,</l>
               <l>to him they went, of him they were eſteemde:</l>
               <l>To garniſhe <hi>Pallas</hi> worke with greater grace,</l>
               <l>By them eche branch and flower had her place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Firre tree firſt her branch they did forbid,</l>
               <l>For it doth ſpeares and warlike weapons make,</l>
               <l>The Oliues branch (whoſe vertue lieth hid)</l>
               <l>It hates, his rootes doe growe from <hi>Limbo</hi> lake,</l>
               <l>The mourning <hi>Cyprus</hi> bowe they did forſake:</l>
               <l>The firſt with redde, but that with black they bounde</l>
               <l>For them (from this) an other vſe was founde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Flowerdeluce though louely to beholde</l>
               <l>In queſtion theſe the wiſeſt did it call,</l>
               <l>And to refuſe the ſame the gods were bolde:</l>
               <l>It repreſentes trouble and cruell thrall,</l>
               <l>The leaues like ſwoordes do grow both tough &amp; tall,</l>
               <l>The roote though pleaſant, poiſon is to ſuch</l>
               <l>As doe it drinke, which made the <hi>Muſes</hi> grutch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe thence for ſecrete cauſe they caſt away,</l>
               <l>As too too bad to haue their being there,</l>
               <l>This comely crewe did ſolemnize that day,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> made her perfite ſkill appeare,</l>
               <l>The <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mphes,</hi> and Ladies of the fountaines cleare</l>
               <l>More buſie then a ſwarme of bees, they brought</l>
               <l>In laden armes ſuch thinges as they had ſought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:20"/>
               <l>A Pantarbe ſtrange of great &amp; goodly ſiſe,</l>
               <l>with workemanſhip as rare as was the ſtone,</l>
               <l>Shee there the firſt foundation did deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Grene graſſe ſhee ſtrowde a handfull thereupon,</l>
               <l>Trefoiles, Cincquefoiles, and caterfoiles among,</l>
               <l>The choſen ſlips of the Pomegranet tree,</l>
               <l>Theſe bound with blacke, with white thoſe did agree,</l>
               <l>whoſe ſecrete ſence <hi>Libethrides</hi> did ſing,</l>
               <l>whilſt <hi>Dryades</hi> did other flowers bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVithin the Salamanders head</l>
               <l>a precious ſtone is founde,</l>
               <l>Of value rich, of vertue rare,</l>
               <l>none ſuch vpon the grounde:</l>
               <l>VVho doth poſſeſſe the ſame,</l>
               <l>may ſtande vnhurt in flame</l>
               <l>of fiers force with fame.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Cupids</hi> might</l>
               <l>Can hurt ſuch one with ſpight,</l>
               <l>Thrice happie wight</l>
               <l>VVho hath the <hi>Pantarbe</hi> found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Graſſe is greene common like corne,</l>
               <l>yet doth it farre ſurmount,</l>
               <l>For only graſſe maintaineth man,</l>
               <l>and is of chiefe account.</l>
               <l>The Romane Captaines wore</l>
               <l>garlandes thereof of yore,</l>
               <l>becauſe they did reſtore</l>
               <l>the quiet peace,</l>
               <l>and made the warres ſurceaſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:21"/>
               <l>A great increaſe</l>
               <l>it plainely doth preſent,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Primeroſe or Caterfoile</l>
               <l>firſt in the prime doth ſpring,</l>
               <l>It is the meſſenger to May</l>
               <l>of wilde flowers the king:</l>
               <l>Who firſt it findes muſt note</l>
               <l>his miſtres by her<note n="*" place="margin">Her colours</note> coat,</l>
               <l>It growes like true loue knot,</l>
               <l>and doth preſent</l>
               <l>ſhee neuer will repent</l>
               <l>her voude intent,</l>
               <l>happie who firſt it findes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cincquefoiles ſanctitie is ſuch,</l>
               <l>the Gentiles did applie</l>
               <l>It chieflly in their ſacrifice</l>
               <l>when they did purifie,</l>
               <l>In it nine colours bin,</l>
               <l>but chiefly white and greene</l>
               <l>the colours of a Queene,</l>
               <l>it doth declare</l>
               <l>The wearer hath great care</l>
               <l>with vertue rare</l>
               <l>to keepe her ſoule from ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Trefoile hath his ſecrete ſenſe,</l>
               <l>the vnitie of three</l>
               <l>It doth declare, and is in league</l>
               <l>with the Pomegranet tree:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:21"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cupid</hi> that braunch did beare,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hand with cruel ſpeare</l>
               <l>Eche louers heart doth teare,</l>
               <l>it doth preſent</l>
               <l>All fleſh to loue is bent,</l>
               <l>and muſt repent</l>
               <l>their loſſe of libertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus though eche Ladie needes muſt loue</l>
               <l>and ſeeke for vnitie,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhee who doth the Pantarbe finde</l>
               <l>ſhall liue at libertie:</l>
               <l>With her reaſon ſhall reſt,</l>
               <l>Fancie ſhall bilde no neſt</l>
               <l>Within her bleſſed breſt,</l>
               <l>the great increaſe</l>
               <l>of perfit loue, and peace,</l>
               <l>ſhall neuer ceaſe,</l>
               <l>VVhere theſe flowers be worne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You happie <hi>Hamadryades</hi>
               </l>
               <l>nowe preſſe you out a pace,</l>
               <l>Bring foorth what beſt may beautifie</l>
               <l>the ſeconde ranke or race:</l>
               <l>This worke is well begunne,</l>
               <l>For wee our parts haue done,</l>
               <l>Now you muſt thither runne,</l>
               <l>in <hi>Pallas</hi> lap</l>
               <l>You muſt your flowers wrap,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mineruas</hi> cap</l>
               <l>Shee wil therewith adorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:22"/>
               <l>Two branches then of euerlaſting wood,</l>
               <l>which neuer will corrupt nor waſte away,</l>
               <l>But euer greene, their ſauour paſſing good,</l>
               <l>They doe declare her fame cannot decay</l>
               <l>VVhich doth them weare, by due deſart I ſay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> them plaſt, and gaue the next degree</l>
               <l>Vnto the Cedar and Geniper tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A thouſand orient pearles ſhee hangde thereon,</l>
               <l>For white with greene will euer well agree,</l>
               <l>Sweete VVilliams then ſhee placed them among,</l>
               <l>And Lauinder for liberalitie:</l>
               <l>For her good workes, a braunche of Sauorie,</l>
               <l>Al theſe the worthie woodbind did imbrace:</l>
               <l>The Honiſuckle gaue a greater grace</l>
               <l>Vnto them all, whoſe braunch with chryſtall dight,</l>
               <l>Did muche increaſe the beholders delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Double Dill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for her humilitie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laus tibi</hi> (health) the Affodill doth ſhewe,</l>
               <l>The Oking braunche her diuturnitie,</l>
               <l>And thereuppon did golden Acornes growe</l>
               <l>In comely knopps, hanging in ſeemely rowe:</l>
               <l>To furniſhe theſe ſhee ſet a ſlip of ſage</l>
               <l>For ſuſtinance, all anger to aſwage</l>
               <l>Next this ſhee gentle Gezemen did place,</l>
               <l>And thrifte ſhe tide within our Ladies lace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> a comely Carbuncle did take,</l>
               <l>whoſe royall rayſe were bright like <hi>Phoebus</hi> bsames,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:22"/>
               <l>A triple towred toppe ſhee ment to make</l>
               <l>Thereon, for well ſhe wiſt the glittering gleames</l>
               <l>Thereof did ſhine with goodly ſtately ſtreames,</l>
               <l>And leand vnto the lookers on ſuch light,</l>
               <l>That they might iudge of euery thing aright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when ſhee had the hearbe Alimon founde,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alaluya</hi> by and by ſhee ſpide,</l>
               <l>The Larkesfoote faſt with white to Burnet bounde,</l>
               <l>Dictamum ſhe to Pencryall tyde,</l>
               <l>with goodly greene ſhee made them all abide:</l>
               <l>And beare the branche whoſe tender twigges did bend,</l>
               <l>with golden fruite as though their rine would rende:</l>
               <l>About the Lillies ſtalke Hearts eaſe was wrapt,</l>
               <l>And loue within our Ladies ſmock ſhee lapt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The pretie Pincke, the goodly Marie golde,</l>
               <l>Muske Roſes mixt with ſeemely Sops in wine,</l>
               <l>Sweete Violets, of colours manifolde,</l>
               <l>The gentle Gyllyflower floriſht fine,</l>
               <l>Roſemary tide vnto a little Time,</l>
               <l>with Baſell, Balme, Iſope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſweete Margerie,</l>
               <l>Theſe were intrayld with branche of Raſper tree</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen then ſhee did the double Daſeye downe</l>
               <l>with blewe ſhee bounde it to the Laurell tree:</l>
               <l>The little Pauncie greateſt of renowme,</l>
               <l>Cornations came with great humilitie,</l>
               <l>Doing vnto ſweete Eglintine dutie:</l>
               <l>And then a branch of Palme with goodly grace,</l>
               <l>Her ſpreading ſpraiſe did beautifie the place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:23"/>
               <l>From hieſt top out of one ſtately ſtemme</l>
               <l>Two royall Roſes white and redde did growe,</l>
               <l>The Oliue tree moſt brauely grew by them,</l>
               <l>And by their rootes were ſet in ſeemely rowe</l>
               <l>Flowers and hearbes whoſe names I doe not knowe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> her comely Casket did vnlocke,</l>
               <l>Before her face the Muſes all did flocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Redroſe firſt with precious pearles they dight,</l>
               <l>The white roſe they inritch with rubies rare,</l>
               <l>Their ſtalke with Azure Saphires garniſht bright</l>
               <l>A ſecrete hidden vertue did declare,</l>
               <l>The Oliues goodly branches were not bare,</l>
               <l>For all her twigges with Emeraulds did bende,</l>
               <l>The Smarage did the Oliues greene amend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of Topazes two ſortes there haue bin founde,</l>
               <l>One ſort like golde this garniſht Eglintine,</l>
               <l>Not on but by the Pauncie moſt renowmde,</l>
               <l>The other much more greene then graſſe did ſhine,</l>
               <l>(By due deſart the Ardonix is thine:)</l>
               <l>Thou doutie double Dayſeie for thy tree</l>
               <l>The Daintie Diamon doth well agree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The other hearbes with Margarites were mixt,</l>
               <l>And heere and there did hang an Amateſt,</l>
               <l>And euerie where a Iaſynth betwixt</l>
               <l>Them both, and comely Chryſtall to the reſt,</l>
               <l>With guled Currall, Bugle of the beſt,</l>
               <l>Spangles of golde and ſiluer there were ſeene,</l>
               <l>All theſe ſet foorth dame <hi>Chloris</hi> goodly greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:23"/>
               <l>The Fayrie Queene did ſeaſon this with ſweet,</l>
               <l>And when ſhe had conſarude it in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>As neither <hi>Brumas</hi> blaſtes, nor <hi>Atumns</hi> heate</l>
               <l>Coulde hurte, ſhee did with all her wit deuiſe,</l>
               <l>From euery branche a ſweete perfume did riſe,</l>
               <l>The flowers did retaine their proper ſmell,</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Pallas</hi> ſtay, this worke is paſſing well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi> and her daintie damſels did</l>
               <l>Their friendly fingers vndefiled frame,</l>
               <l>When ſacred ſolemne rites were finiſhed,</l>
               <l>To beare being whithout or blot or blame</l>
               <l>Vnto her grace who was of greateſt fame</l>
               <l>This rare deuiſe, with double dignitie</l>
               <l>Meaning to crowne <hi>Mineruas</hi> maieſtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Poets Pince, and Harauldes chiefeſt king</l>
               <l>Mightie <hi>Palaphilos</hi> you might perſaue</l>
               <l>To place ech one appointing euerie thing</l>
               <l>As it ſhoulde bee: the gods were bounſing braue,</l>
               <l>No goddeſſe there, no muſe nor <hi>Nymphe</hi> was graue,</l>
               <l>All did with ioyfull Iubilie reioyce</l>
               <l>Shouting <hi>Minerua</hi> liues with often voyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then might you ſee the rurall dames come in,</l>
               <l>The youth like frie, olde folke like foules did flocke:</l>
               <l>With bags and baskits filde vp to the brimme,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Fauni</hi> did the Forreſt gates vnlocke:</l>
               <l>And ſimple Cate clad in a ruſſet frocke</l>
               <l>Brought branches thence, and flowers aporne full,</l>
               <l>The waies were woods made by the gadding ſcull,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:24"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> tooke in hand his pleaſant Lute,</l>
               <l>And hee his Harp who ſaid <hi>Euridicen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thales</hi> did force with louely lippes her Flute,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calliope</hi> on Sitarne did begin,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomene</hi> on Viall prayſe did winne,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Napeae</hi> with the <hi>Nayades</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They did deuiſe and ſinge thes ſweete ditties.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Nymphes</hi> and Ladies of the lake,</l>
               <l>Perfourme this great ſolemnitie</l>
               <l>All for their new <hi>Mineruas</hi> ſake</l>
               <l>noble <hi>Naiades.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And where renowmed <hi>Napea</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is ſhee who doth deſerue ſuch fame?</l>
               <l>In England now <hi>Naiades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With flant a flant this flanting flocke,</l>
               <l>The greateſt goddeſſe by degree,</l>
               <l>They meane that maiden Queene to make</l>
               <l>with royall dignitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thither goe all this faire flocke</l>
               <l>with ſuch ſo great ſolemnitie,</l>
               <l>All for their newe <hi>Mineruas</hi> ſake</l>
               <l>noble <hi>Naiades.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus they at laſt were come where Lud had laid</l>
               <l>Though not the firſt, foundations long before,</l>
               <l>VVhere then this courtly maiden Queene ſhe ſtaide</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:24"/>
               <l>With all her traine, and manie ſtraingers more</l>
               <l>For then there were Ambaſſadors great ſtore:</l>
               <l>Whom to delight, the people did prepare</l>
               <l>Triumphes, perfourmde with courage paſſing rare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The court it ſelfe none ſuch my ſelfe haue ſeene</l>
               <l>In <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in <hi>Spayne,</hi> nor curious <hi>Italie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The courtiers, firſt the beautie of the Queene,</l>
               <l>Her goodly grace, her garments what they bee,</l>
               <l>No Empreſſe can make ſuch ſhowe as ſhee,</l>
               <l>For gold, for pearle, for precious ſtones of price,</l>
               <l>No one like her for robes of rare deuiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then from the prince vnto the poreſt page,</l>
               <l>The worſte in ſilke, the beſt in cloth of golde</l>
               <l>Richly inricht, the noble man ſo ſage,</l>
               <l>The gentleman ſo ciuell to beholde,</l>
               <l>The courteous ſeruing man the boy though bolde,</l>
               <l>Yet he and they eche one in his degree,</l>
               <l>Did plainely proue him ſelfe ciuilitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Titans</hi> beames had baniſht <hi>Lunas</hi> light</l>
               <l>And duskiſh dim which dide the day with darke,</l>
               <l>Sent foorth from fame <hi>report</hi> that worthie wight,</l>
               <l>With trompet ſhrille made heauen and earth to harke,</l>
               <l>Immortall gods and mortall men did marke</l>
               <l>The meſſage which with great ſolemnitie,</l>
               <l>was thus declarde to all of each degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſheuered ſtaues will well declare the minde</l>
               <l>Of them who heere this day will ſhowe their might,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:25"/>
               <l>An Earle by birth and of an noble kinde</l>
               <l>His chalenge will perfourme euen in deſpight</l>
               <l>Of him or them which dare withſtande in fight,</l>
               <l>Therefore you <hi>Brutes</hi> which would inrich your name</l>
               <l>Caſt armour one and trie the Tilte for fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Mertials and the Iudges had their place,</l>
               <l>The Harraldes preſt to pen eche due deſart,</l>
               <l>The Queene was come, there waited on her grace</l>
               <l>A hundred Ladies beautifull and braue,</l>
               <l>The forraine princes and her counſaile graue,</l>
               <l>When all the ſhowe and euery thing was ſeene</l>
               <l>No colours cold compare with white and greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The challenger proudly preſumde to ſay</l>
               <l>That white and greene had not the braueſt hewe,</l>
               <l>But that his Maiſtris bore the bell away:</l>
               <l>Her courtly colours were moſt worthie vewe</l>
               <l>Hee ſaide and ſwore, wherewith the trumpets blewe,</l>
               <l>The ſplents of ſpeares which climde the cloudes aboue</l>
               <l>Did well declare the force of mightie loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Fierce defendant with a counter buffe</l>
               <l>Of this proud chalenger did chaunge the cheere,</l>
               <l>Spight of his force and all his cootes of proffe</l>
               <l>He made him leaue the fielde for feeble feare,</l>
               <l>Aſſiſtantes three forthwith there did appeare,</l>
               <l>The firſt did well, the ſecond in his place,</l>
               <l>So did the thirde but for this one diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Helmet for the honour of his deare</l>
               <l>The Ladie whom they all did moſt commend,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:25"/>
               <l>Her gallant plume and colours he did weare,</l>
               <l>Which for her ſake like life he did defende:</l>
               <l>Yet force perforce, them to the ground did ſende:</l>
               <l>And then the people cride God ſaue the Queene,</l>
               <l>No colours can compare with white and green.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therewith the cloud which did the gods incloſe</l>
               <l>That they might walke, and ſee, and not be ſeene,</l>
               <l>Was quit with drawne, the people did ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Heauen was broke looſe, ſo might the royall Queene,</l>
               <l>So did the court, ſo all the worlde might deeme,</l>
               <l>The armed knightes the people in a traunce</l>
               <l>Did muſe, and makt the order of this chaunce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Saturne</hi> and vii. ſages paſt before,</l>
               <l>Then mightie <hi>Mars</hi> with him ix. worthies went,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptune</hi> he had three ſaylers and no more,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Caſtor and Pollux.</note> two for a learned intent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silenus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Preachers.</note> v. all v. from heauen were ſent,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Mercury</hi> the ruler<note n="*" place="margin">Fame.</note> of report,</l>
               <l>Thus theſe vi. gods entred into the court.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next theſe dame <hi>Floras</hi> noble <hi>Nymphes</hi> came in,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Fayerie</hi> Queene, and Ladies of the lake,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi> and her Damſels then were ſeene,</l>
               <l>A troupe which did to chaſtitie betake</l>
               <l>Themſelues, come thither for <hi>Mineruas</hi> ſake,</l>
               <l>There <hi>Pallas</hi> and the learned <hi>Muſes</hi> ſtaid,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pallas</hi> thus vnto <hi>Minerua</hi> ſayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt mightie prince almightie <hi>Ioue</hi> the iuſt</l>
               <l>Would vs on earth ſhowe whom he beſt doth loue,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:26"/>
               <l>We haue inquirde, and nowe it is diſcuſt</l>
               <l>It is thy ſelfe, whom he who ſittes aboue</l>
               <l>Hath ſo inricht that thou canſt not remoue,</l>
               <l>From that which with his will doth well agree,</l>
               <l>Being of all the beſt felicitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nowe ſith we ſee thy goodly gouernment,</l>
               <l>And finde howe paſſing ſtraight thy ſteps do ſtand,</l>
               <l>We all be come, all wee for this intent</l>
               <l>To liue with thee, to bee at thy commande,</l>
               <l>And for that cauſe <hi>Pallas</hi> and all her bande,</l>
               <l>Doth heere reſigne vnto thy worthie will</l>
               <l>Their worldly wit, and all their learned skill,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy due deſert hath thee <hi>Minerua</hi> made</l>
               <l>A goddeſſe great, with whom none can compare,</l>
               <l>For hee of heauen hath ſet it downe and ſaid,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Britttain</hi> Queene ſhalbe that Phoenix rare,</l>
               <l>Whom death to touch with dart ſhall neuer dare:</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt on earth eternally remaine</l>
               <l>As I haue done, though greater be thy gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beholde theſe gods all readie to reſigne</l>
               <l>The giftes for which they were eternized,</l>
               <l>Receiue thou them becauſe they be all thine,</l>
               <l>Receiue alſo vnto thy heauenly head</l>
               <l>This Corronet, this garlande garniſhed</l>
               <l>Not like thy minde with gifts of greateſt price,</l>
               <l>But as we coulde inricht with rare deuiſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee thus adornd with double dignitie</l>
               <l>They did of mortall her immortall make,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:26"/>
               <l>As thus ſhee ſat amidſt ſuch maieſtie</l>
               <l>The lookers on with louing feare did ſhake,</l>
               <l>Her goodly grace did make the gods to quake:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> then and all the people ſaid</l>
               <l>thy due deſert hath thee <hi>Minerua</hi> made.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then the Queene with more then mortall grace,</l>
               <l>The life (quoth ſhee) of euery liuing thing</l>
               <l>Muſt periſh quite, for death will it deface:</l>
               <l>But death to death by due deſert to bring</l>
               <l>Such death on earth is life euerlaſting,</l>
               <l>I knowe right well ſuch immortalitie</l>
               <l>you haue obtainde, and ſuch remaines for me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then forth from the ſlender ſuttel skies</l>
               <l>All Angellike there did a ſhape appeare,</l>
               <l>Euen as it is of ghoſts deuine the giſe</l>
               <l>A heauenly humane forme ſhee did on there:</l>
               <l>And yet ſhee was as <hi>Tytans</hi> beames ſo cleare,</l>
               <l>Immaculate not hauing ſpot of ſinne,</l>
               <l>All clad in white thus did her grace begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Within this worlde at laſt is one</l>
               <l>who hath inricht her name</l>
               <l>with euerlaſting fame,</l>
               <l>This Ladie only ſhee alone</l>
               <l>ſhee ſhall inioy the ſame:</l>
               <l>the goddeſſes diuine,</l>
               <l>and all the <hi>Muſes</hi> ix.</l>
               <l>to her they ſhall reſigne:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:27"/>
               <l>Becauſe the due deſartes which them immortal made</l>
               <l>This Ladie hath obtaind, her fame ſhall neuer fade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proceed my <hi>Muſe</hi> aſſiſt thy ſeruaunt nowe,</l>
               <l>Able his penne to publiſhe forth her praiſe</l>
               <l>Whoſe life is like dame <hi>Sinthias</hi> ſiluer rayſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That mightie God of heauen <hi>Ioua</hi> great,</l>
               <l>He doth permit, his highnes doth alowe</l>
               <l>Vnto her grace all earthly bleſſe ſhall bowe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And bide, and bee at her commaundement,</l>
               <l>With perfit bleſſe to beautifie her ſeate,</l>
               <l>Euen for that cauſe <hi>Euthumia</hi> is ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With her this goddeſſe euermore ſhall ſtay,</l>
               <l>Then thus beſpake bleſſed <hi>Euthumia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Goddeſſe of great accompt</l>
               <l>whoſe due deſert doth farre ſurmount</l>
               <l>the peoples prayſe,</l>
               <l>in no ſuch wayſe</l>
               <l>did euer woman walke:</l>
               <l>Faire Ladie ſweet with thee, with thee I meane to talke,</l>
               <l>Talke and reſigne to thee, euen to thy ſelfe my ſtate,</l>
               <l>of all the world moſt fortunate,</l>
               <l>whoſe happines</l>
               <l>with perfit bleſſe</l>
               <l>is furniſhed, nowe I muſt dwell</l>
               <l>with thee, becauſe thou doeſt excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:27"/>
               <l>Thy vertues rare</l>
               <l>Do well declare</l>
               <l>To what thou art inclinde,</l>
               <l>The worthines of woman kinde,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt approue that ſexe is ſuch</l>
               <l>As doth mankinde exceed, exceedeth man by much,</l>
               <l>By muche and moſte of all, of all the royall reſte,</l>
               <l>Thy perfite greate eſtate is beſte,</l>
               <l>Thy birth right great, greater thy fame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euthumias</hi> noble name</l>
               <l>I yeelde to thee</l>
               <l>my dignitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy due deſerued right, in deede thy right rewarde</l>
               <l>Rewarded by the gods, for when the gods had harde</l>
               <l>In what a perfit path you tread,</l>
               <l>And howe your life you leade,</l>
               <l>They did ordaine</l>
               <l>Mee to remaine</l>
               <l>With her whoſe ſtate</l>
               <l>Was fortunate,</l>
               <l>So ſent from them to you,</l>
               <l>to you, onely to you I bowe,</l>
               <l>And bende, and bind my ſelfe, my ſelfe vnto your will,</l>
               <l>Your wil? that is my worke, my worke that to fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweet Eglintine ſhall haue the place,</l>
               <l>And notice of thy name,</l>
               <l>Which flowre to defend, euen to defende the ſame,</l>
               <l>Of paſſing puſiant power</l>
               <l>In hieſt throne</l>
               <l>Hee which doth ſit, he ſhall defende</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:28"/>
               <l>thee from thy fone,</l>
               <l>and ſo preſerue the ſeate, the ſeat where thou doſt ſit,</l>
               <l>as neither hatreds heate</l>
               <l>nor wicked wit,</l>
               <l>ſhall bloot thy goodnes with diſgrace,</l>
               <l>amongſt the gods thou ſhalt remaine</l>
               <l>for euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aglaia</hi> moſt like the morning ſtarre</l>
               <l>that godeſſe next <hi>Euthumia</hi> did appeare,</l>
               <l>none of the muſes might with her compare,</l>
               <l>muche like her ſelfe ſhee found <hi>Minerua</hi> there:</l>
               <l>Suche beutie, bountie, perſonage and grace,</l>
               <l>Greatlie amazde ſhe pauſde a prettie ſpace:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> then did downe his mightie mace,</l>
               <l>He thus deſcribd the fauour of her face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like newe refined golde Queene <hi>Hellens</hi> haire,</l>
               <l>Shee hath the browes of bliſſed <hi>Briſſis</hi> braue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egerias</hi> eie, ſhee hath <hi>Egeſtas</hi> eare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chionis</hi> cheeke, and <hi>Chloris</hi> goodly grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neeras</hi> noſe on fayre <hi>Venus</hi> face,</l>
               <l>The tongue of <hi>Teleſilla, Tethis</hi> teeth,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ledas</hi> lippes to lende louely reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of modeſt <hi>Myrta</hi> milde the ſmiling cheere,</l>
               <l>Dame <hi>Floras</hi> breth ſo ſweet as violet,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clitias</hi> chin, like <hi>Collitina</hi> cleare,</l>
               <l>The necke of <hi>Nemeſis, Doris,</hi> or <hi>Eudora,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her breſts be braue like <hi>Diopeia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shee is of all the worlde the brighteſt ſtarre,</l>
               <l>Begot by <hi>Mars</hi> the mightie god of warre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:28"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> ſtaide, <hi>Aglaia</hi> did proceede</l>
               <l>Though much amazde to ſee as t'were her ſelf,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aglaias</hi> eyes they on her face did feede,</l>
               <l>And coulde not ſatisfie themſelues with ſight,</l>
               <l>There was containd in it ſo great delight:</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt her wordes did well diſplay</l>
               <l>Her in warde thought, thus did the Ladie ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lady of all delight</l>
               <l>Delight of Ladies all,</l>
               <l>All the moſt worthie wight</l>
               <l>Moſt worthie wight they ſhall,</l>
               <l>Shall they? They ſhall in deed,</l>
               <l>Indeed, adore thy name,</l>
               <l>Thy name wth euerlaſting fame.</l>
               <l>Fame flie thou foorth with ſpeede,</l>
               <l>VVith ſpeede let it be knowne to all vnder the Sunne,</l>
               <l>The Sun hath ſhinde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none ſuch ſince firſt the world begun.</l>
               <l>To whom <hi>Aglaia</hi> doth reſigne,</l>
               <l>For new <hi>Mineruas</hi> prayſe doth ſhine</l>
               <l>More bright then heretofore did mine:</l>
               <l>VVith all a flaunt a flaunt,</l>
               <l>Thou as thou ſhouldſt doſt vaunt,</l>
               <l>The Gods of heauen doe graunt</l>
               <l>Thee euermore their heauenly grace,</l>
               <l>To proſper thee in euerie place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That goodly goddeſſe great renowmed <hi>Clytia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſhe preſt into the preſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus the dame diuine did ſay,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:29"/>
               <l>Braue Beſſe how are delights</l>
               <l>Of beauties braueſt bright</l>
               <l>Plaſt in thy paſſing perfect perſonage,</l>
               <l>Stand foorth you worthie wights</l>
               <l>Beholde you heere in ſight,</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt glorie of this preſent age:</l>
               <l>Vnto this gallant gay</l>
               <l>Doth worthie <hi>Clytia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>her name and fame reſigne,</l>
               <l>All glory hath beene mine,</l>
               <l>All glory nowe is thine,</l>
               <l>With glory thou doſt ſhine, ſo like the ſeemly Sunne,</l>
               <l>Braue Beſſe ſhal be thy name when al the world is done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next her appeard a muſe of great degree,</l>
               <l>And thus beſpake comelie <hi>Calliope,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Ladie like my ſelfe at laſt,</l>
               <l>at laſt my ſelfe haue founde,</l>
               <l>that ſhee may be renowmde:</l>
               <l>Fame telles her name with buſie blaſt</l>
               <l>To all vpon the ground:</l>
               <l>The ſweetneſſe of her voice</l>
               <l>Doth make the gods reioyce,</l>
               <l>Therefore <hi>Calliope</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To little Englands worthie Queene</l>
               <l>Doth giue her great degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then the Graces called <hi>Charytes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With theſe ſpeeches did all the people pleaſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Amidſt a gallant gardine greene,</l>
               <l>Where natures worthieſt worke is ſeene,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:29"/>
               <l>Impald with perfect bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Wherein one forme our ſelues haue founde</l>
               <l>All the good graces on the grounde,</l>
               <l>Euen there our biding is,</l>
               <l>With mery mindes wee there remaine,</l>
               <l>The place doth pleaſe vs ſo,</l>
               <l>It neuer ſhall bee ſeene nor ſaide,</l>
               <l>That wee from thence will goe:</l>
               <l>As foode feedes mortall fleſhe,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo our mindes doe eate</l>
               <l>The perfect pleaſures there doe grow,</l>
               <l>Moſt meete for Angels meate:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dido</hi> that courtly <hi>Carthage</hi> Queene,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Troyes</hi> decay that fine <hi>Helen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And gallant <hi>Venus</hi> gay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuno</hi> nor <hi>Pallas</hi> neuer dare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi> chaſte may not compare,</l>
               <l>With mightie <hi>Minerua<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſhee hath that which all they had,</l>
               <l>In much more perfect plight</l>
               <l>Then minde of man imagine may,</l>
               <l>Or Dittie can indight:</l>
               <l>VVe vaunt not then in vaine,</l>
               <l>For only wee are bleſt</l>
               <l>VVho doe inioy of all the worlde</l>
               <l>the very worthieſt:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Inioy? wee only doe poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>The higheſt haight of happineſſe,</l>
               <l>Therefore wee will reioyce,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:30"/>
               <l>For where all vertue doth remaine</l>
               <l>Euen ſhee who all the reſt doth ſtaine</l>
               <l>is made our only choyce.</l>
               <l>And this to you of heauen we vowe,</l>
               <l>whilſt you her life do lend</l>
               <l>Only with her we will remaine,</l>
               <l>our faith ſhall her defend,</l>
               <l>her becke wee will obey,</l>
               <l>I ſhee ſhall haue our heart,</l>
               <l>and we with her wil runne and ride</l>
               <l>wee neuer will depart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On earth heauenly felicitie</l>
               <l>euen heere on earth not one but wee,</l>
               <l>and wee haue found the place,</l>
               <l>VVhere euery perfect ſweete delight</l>
               <l>doth reſt, and doth remaine by right:</l>
               <l>wee doe the branche imbrace,</l>
               <l>whoſe buds the bloſſomes bee of bliſſe,</l>
               <l>whoſe fruite <hi>Ambroſia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God keepe <hi>Minerua</hi> from miſhap,</l>
               <l>God keepe her from decay,</l>
               <l>For with that goddeſſe greate</l>
               <l>wee doe poſſeſſe our place,</l>
               <l>And wee will dwell for euermore</l>
               <l>in her moſt faire face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Clio</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Calliope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That modeſt mery <hi>Muſe</hi> of great degree,</l>
               <l>Found out this Queene who had her goodly grace,</l>
               <l>ſhee all her giftes and goodnes did imbrace,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:30"/>
               <l>Whome longe ſhe did with maruell muche beholde,</l>
               <l>Thus ſhee at laſt her fancies did vnfolde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Macthleſſe for muſick once I was,</l>
               <l>none could my note come neere,</l>
               <l>nowe thou doſt paſſe,</l>
               <l>thy voyce moſt cleere</l>
               <l>From healtfull lights and lounges belowe doth ſend,</l>
               <l>Such ſweete and pleaſant harmonie,</l>
               <l>The gods their eares doe bende,</l>
               <l>And after thee</l>
               <l>we ſee</l>
               <l>The reſt of all the Muſes run,</l>
               <l>to gaze vpon thy grace,</l>
               <l>Which as they do behold they finde,</l>
               <l>thy mothers faire face,</l>
               <l>to thee</l>
               <l>I <hi>Clio</hi> heere</l>
               <l>Doe giue eternitie,</l>
               <l>Thou noble <hi>Nymphe</hi> that haſt no peere,</l>
               <l>Thy name and fame ſhall liue and neuer fade,</l>
               <l>The onely peece of worke that euer nature made</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ſhee who once was but a mortall Queene,</l>
               <l>And ſubiect ſate on fortunes turning wheele,</l>
               <l>The greateſt goddeſſe nowe on earth is ſeene:</l>
               <l>Whoſe hie eſtate can neither roule nor reele,</l>
               <l>Nor fortunes force ſhall neuer hurt her heele:</l>
               <l>For vertue did and due deſart aduaunce</l>
               <l>Her grace, and not the force of changing chance,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4849:31"/>
               <l>Shee is not nowe as other princes bee,</l>
               <l>Who liue on earth to euery tempeſt thrall,</l>
               <l>Deſert hath crownde her with eternitie,</l>
               <l>Her godly zeale in ſeate ſempiternal</l>
               <l>Hath ſet her nowe, from thence ſhee can not fall:</l>
               <l>But liuely liue on earth eternally:</l>
               <l>And haue in heauen heauenly felicitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therewith this curious court brake vp, and I in ragged rime</l>
               <l>Was made the trumpet to their talk, the touchſtone of the time.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the gods there is none like thee O Lorde,</l>
               <l>There is none can do as thou doeſt. <bibl>Pſal. Lxxxvi.</bibl>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>The Pilgrimes poſtſcrip.</head>
            <l>Euermore my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhall magnifie thy name</l>
            <l>Moſt gracious, moſt right renowned dame</l>
            <l>Nowe that I knowe thy due deſerued fame:</l>
            <l>moſt mightie prince the meanes thou haſt made</l>
            <l>that all the world doth knowe</l>
            <l>howe vertue like a ſea doth flowe</l>
            <l>in thee, and howe thou doeſt forſlake</l>
            <l>the bitter bent of cruell <hi>Caepides</hi> bowe,</l>
            <l>free fro the force of fancies flaſhing flame,</l>
            <l>Moſt gratious, moſt right renowned dame</l>
            <l>Nowe that I knowe thy due deſerued fame,</l>
            <l>Euermore my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhall magnifie thy name:</l>
            <l>firſt with thy wit who can compare,</l>
            <l>thy vertuous inclination</l>
            <l>is knowne to euery nation,</l>
            <l>thy learning and thy gifts moſt rare</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:4849:31"/>
            <l>make perfite declaration</l>
            <l>nature thy equall neuer yet did frame.</l>
            <l>Nowe that I knowe thy due deſerued fame</l>
            <l>Euermore my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhall magnifie thy name,</l>
            <l>Moſt gracious, moſt right renowned dame.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties poore pilgrime, <hi>Thomas Blener Haſſet.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Heere endeth the firſt booke of the reuelation of the true Minerua.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London at the three <hi>Cranes in the Vintree by Thomas</hi> Dawſon, for Thomas Woodcoke.</p>
            <p>1582.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
